- This video is about one of
the most important questions:
what leads to a happy life?
- Realistically, money.
- Being wealthy is definitely
a big aspect of it.
- To save a lot of money.
- Money.
- Earning money.
- It's very important to be rich.
- It's easy for people
to say they don't care about having money
and that money can't buy happiness,
but that's really not true.
- 'Cause I would rather cry on a yacht
than in a like a Subaru.
(both laugh)
- [Derek] Clearly, having
a successful career
and financial wealth
are important to people.
Is there a number in mind?
Something you wanna get to?
- At least a million.
- Yeah?
- Yeah.
- In a survey from 2018
of around a hundred
thousand college freshmen,
about 55% said they wanted to
be successful in their career
and 83% reported that they
wanted to become rich.
But do these accomplishments
really increase happiness?
Well, that's what I wanna
find out in this video.
But how do you study
what makes people happy?
Well, you can ask them.
What's gonna make you happy?
- Um.
- Uh.
- Ooh.
- [Derek] But people aren't really good
at judging what will make them happy.
Winning the lottery seems
like it should make you happy.
- What!?
(sister screams)
What!? What!?
- [Derek] But numerous
studies on lottery winners
find that after the initial
surge of happiness wears off,
many are no happier than the rest of us.
Some are, in fact, more miserable
than they were beforehand.
- 'Cause you don't see as many
people as you used to see.
Obviously, you become slightly isolated,
I think in some ways.
- Yeah, I agree.
- Another problem is that
people's memories aren't reliable.
- We only detect, encode
and store in our brains
bits and pieces of the entire
experience in front of us.
It's called reconstructed memories.
It happens to us
in all the aspects of
our lives all the time.
- Most studies on
happiness find older people
and ask them to recall
what made them happy.
But as we've just seen,
memory is unreliable.
So a better way to conduct a study
would be to follow people
throughout their entire lives,
capturing the choices they make
and how those affect their happiness.
That is really hard to do.
But there is one study like this
that's been running since 1938.
Now, 85 years is a long
time to run a study
so it has been passed down
from one generation of
researchers to the next.
It's currently run by its fourth
director, Robert Waldinger.
What is the claim to
fame then of the study?
- You know, the claim
to fame is that it is,
as far as we know, the longest
study of human development
that's ever been done.
The longest study of any depth.
These are studies that take
deep dives into people's lives
and their mental and physical health.
- [Derek] The study actually
began as two separate studies
by two groups of Harvard researchers
that didn't know about each other.
The first group followed
268 young men from Harvard
to find out how they would
develop into early adulthood.
- So of course,
if you wanna study normal
young adult development,
you study all white guys
from Harvard, right?
(Derek laughs)
You know, it's one of those limitations.
- [Derek] The second
group studied 456 boys
from middle school onwards
from Boston's poorest and
most disadvantaged families.
- So there were these two studies,
both meant to be studies of
what goes right in development
and how we predict who
does well as they grow up.
- Eventually, the two
studies merged into one:
The Harvard Study of Adult Development.
At the start of the study, the
participants were interviewed
and received extensive
physical examinations.
And as they grew, they
entered all walks of life.
Some of them became
bricklayers and doctors
and factory workers and lawyers,
and one even became president
of the United States.
(presidential music)
Every two years, researchers
ask them questions
about their lives.
Like, "If you could stop
working without loss of income,
would you, what would you do instead?
How often do you feel
isolated from others?
True or false, life has
more pain than pleasure."
And other questions about their marriage,
career, friendships, and their
physical and mental health.
While the study started
with just 724 participants,
over time, their spouses and children
were also included in the study.
So how many people are
we talking about in total
who have been part of the study?
- Between 2,500 and 3,000
people altogether in the study.
- [Derek] And as technology improved,
so did the methods of data collection.
- We now draw blood from DNA.
You know, DNA wasn't
even imagined in 1938.
We measure messenger RNA, DNA methylation,
we bring people into our laboratory,
we deliberately stress them out
and then see how quickly
they recover from stress.
Looking at heart rate
variability, for example,
looking at cortisol deposited in hair,
because that seems to
be a long-term measure
of circulating cortisol.
But all of these new
methods are in the service
of studying the same big phenomena
of human wellbeing.
- So what do 85 years of research
across entire human lives teach us
about a healthy and happy life?
- Two huge takeaways really.
One is no surprise.
It's that if you take care
of your physical health,
it has huge benefits, not
just for your longevity,
but for how long you stay healthy.
Eating well, getting regular exercise,
not abusing alcohol or drugs, not smoking,
getting preventive healthcare,
exercise is hugely important.
- [Derek] A Taiwanese study
looked at the medical data
of 416,000 healthy people
between 1996 and 2008.
Eight years later, they
followed up with each person
to look at the link between
exercise and mortality.
They found that people who
exercised just 15 minutes a day
had a 14% reduced risk of dying,
and a three year longer life expectancy.
Every additional 15 minutes of exercise
decreased the risk of
dying by an extra 4%.
A large meta-analysis from 2008 confirms
that people who are physically active
have a reduced risk of dying
during the timeframes
investigated in each study.
Exercise also protects
our cognitive health.
A meta-analysis from 2014 found
that participants with higher
levels of physical activity
had a 35% reduced risk
of cognitive decline
and a 14% reduced risk of dementia.
- And then the big surprising
finding is, relationships,
not just keeping us happier,
but keeping us healthier
and helping us live longer.
- It's not just the Harvard study.
There's now a whole list of studies
that show the importance of relationships
to human happiness and health.
They teach us three main lessons.
The first is that relationships
are great for our health.
In 2010, researchers
looked across 148 studies
with a total of more than
300,000 participants.
They found that, on average,
people with stronger social connections
had a 50% increased likelihood of survival
for any given year.
Being married, in particular,
has a large impact on
how long people live.
- There's one study, I think
it's pretty well respected,
that suggests that married men
live 12 years longer on
average than unmarried men
and married women live seven
years longer on average
than unmarried women.
Marriage is always a better
deal for men on all parameters
than it is for women.
(Derek laughs)
And it's not because you have
a marriage license, right?
It's because people living together
in an intimate partnership
tend to keep each other healthier.
You have somebody who's kind of watching,
looking out for you.
It's a very real, concrete effect.
- If feeling well-connected to others
makes us happier, healthier,
and extends our lives,
then what happens if we feel disconnected?
- There's a researcher,
Julianne Holt-Lunstad,
out of the University of Utah,
who did a meta-analysis
of a whole slew of studies
of the physical effects of loneliness.
And her calculation was that being lonely
is as dangerous to your health
as smoking half a pack
of cigarettes a day,
or as dangerous as being obese.
- [Derek] Feeling disconnected from others
also makes you more prone to disease.
A large meta-analysis from 2016
found that poor social relationships
were associated with a 29%
increase in risk of heart disease
and a 32% increase in risk of stroke.
- So these have real sort
of quantifiable consequences
when we look at studies
of thousands of people.
- One caveat is that most studies
on the health effects of loneliness
focus on people aged 50 and older.
(clock ticking)
And loneliness is on the rise.
- The U.S. Surgeon General today
declared a new public
health epidemic in America.
Loneliness.
- We're now finding that one in two adults
report measurable levels of loneliness
and it turns out that young
people are most affected.
And here's why this is so concerning.
It's because we've realized
that loneliness is more
than just a bad feeling.
It has real consequences
for our mental and physical health.
- The UK has appointed a
minister of loneliness.
Many, many countries are concerned
about this breakdown in social connection.
- A question about loneliness,
like, what does that look like?
Because, obviously, everyone experiences
some periods of loneliness.
So you know, when does it become
sort of really detrimental
and how do we define that?
- Well, loneliness is different
from being alone, right?
So you can be alone and quite content,
and many people are, in fact.
The ability to be
content when you're alone
is quite a skill and
it's a wonderful ability.
Loneliness is that subjective experience
of being less connected to
people than you wanna be.
And that's why, you know,
you can be lonely in a crowd.
We're all on a spectrum
between extroversion,
you know, wanting lots
of people in our lives,
and introversion, actually
needing a lot of solitude
and not wanting a lot of people,
a lot of people are
stressful for introverts.
And what we know is that
neither one is healthier, right?
Like introverts are perfectly healthy.
They just may need one or two
really solid relationships
and don't want a lot more people.
Nothing wrong with that at all.
Whereas extroverts may want
lots of people in their lives.
- [Derek] So the second lesson is
that it's not how many
people you know or see,
or even whether you're married or not,
because a bad marriage can be worse
for your health than getting divorced.
Instead, it's about the quality
of your close relationships that matters.
- When we'd followed
all the original people
out to their 80s we said,
"Okay, what data actually
are the best predictors
at age 50 of who's gonna be happy
and healthy at age 80 as
opposed to sick or dead?"
And we thought we were gonna be looking
at blood pressure and
cholesterol level at age 50
as the strongest predictors.
It was their relationships.
It was particularly their satisfaction
with their marital relationships
that was the strongest predictor.
- And relationships don't
just keep us happier
and physically healthier,
they also protect our brains.
People who are in secure
relationships in their 80s,
where they feel that they
can rely on the other person,
find that their memories
stay sharper for longer.
And people who feel lonely,
well, their memories fade quicker.
A study of retired U.S. adults found
that the rate of cognitive decline
was 20% higher over 10 years
for those who felt lonely.
A meta-analysis from 2018 further confirms
the detrimental effects of loneliness,
finding that it also increased
the risk of dementia.
But there's still a big open question:
what is it about the relationships
that makes them particularly
healthful or helpful?
- The best hypothesis,
for which there's some
pretty decent research now,
is that relationships
are emotion regulators.
They're stress regulators.
So stressful things happen every day
to many of us, right?
So then what happens?
Well, the body goes into
fight-or-flight mode,
blood pressure goes up,
respirations become more rapid,
circulating stress hormone levels rise.
But then the body is meant
to go back to equilibrium
after that normal fight-or-flight response
when we face a challenge.
If I can come home and there's
somebody here to talk to,
I can literally feel my body calm down.
What we are pretty sure happens
is that people who are isolated,
that they're more likely
to stay in a kind of chronic
fight-or-flight mode.
And that what that means is
that they have higher levels
of circulating cortisol,
higher levels of chronic inflammation,
and that those things gradually
wear away body systems.
So that's how, for example,
chronic stress can predict
coronary artery disease,
but also arthritis and
also type-two diabetes
because of this common mechanism
that breaks down multiple body systems.
- The key to preventing
this breakdown is simple.
Just spend a little more time
with the people you care about.
Unfortunately, we seem to
be doing the exact opposite.
Before going into why we're
doing the exact opposite,
this part of the video was
sponsored by BetterHelp.
There are many things
that can negatively impact our happiness.
It could be stress or fear or
a clinical mental health issue
like depression or anxiety.
But regardless of which one it is,
therapy can help you
by giving you the tools
to approach your life
in a very different way.
And that's where BetterHelp comes in.
They connect you with an
experienced, licensed therapist
who is trained to listen
and give you helpful, unbiased advice.
I know that finding a
good therapist is hard,
especially when you only have
the options in your city.
But BetterHelp changes the game on this
because it's an online platform.
And by filling out a few questions,
you'll get matched with
a professional therapist.
So you can get talking in
most cases within 48 hours
and then you can have your
therapy session as a phone call,
as a video chat, or even via
messaging if you prefer that.
Just whatever's the
most comfortable version
of therapy for you.
And it's easy to sign up, there's
a link in the description.
It is betterhelp.com/veritasium.
Clicking on that link both
helps support this channel
and it also gets you 10% off
your first month of BetterHelp.
So you can try it out
and see if it helps you.
And if you don't really fit
with your first therapist,
which is pretty common,
you can easily switch
to a new one for free
without stressing about insurance,
who's in your network
or anything like that.
If you feel like you could
benefit from talking to someone,
getting feedback, advice,
and help for anything
that might be affecting your
happiness and progress in life,
then visit betterhelp.com/veritasium
or click that link in
the description below.
So I want to thank BetterHelp
for sponsoring this part of the video.
And now, back to the
importance of relationships.
There is an alarming trend in our society.
- [Newsreader] Social engagement
with friends decreased
from 60 minutes a day in 2003
to just 20 minutes a day in 2020.
- The technology has fundamentally changed
how we interact with one another
and how we communicate with one another
and, unfortunately, has often replaced
what used to be rich in-person connections
with online connections, which
often are of lower quality.
- Now, you may say you're an introvert
and you don't need to
spend much time with people
to feel good.
And while it's true that
introverts and extroverts
need different amounts
of social stimulation,
both need human connection.
In 2015, Holt-Lunstad and her colleagues
looked at the data of
70 independent studies
with more than 3 million
total participants.
Similar to other studies,
they found that the subjective
feeling of loneliness
increased the risk of
premature death by 26%.
But they also looked at
the objective measure of social isolation,
how much time you're actually
spending with other people.
And they found that social isolation
increased the risk of
premature death by 29%.
And unfortunately,
introverts are more at risk
of being socially isolated.
Just like many young people today,
many participants from the Harvard study
also believed that money and achievement
were what they should go
after to have a good life.
But what this study and
plenty of others show
is that the people who were the happiest
were those that leaned
into their relationships
with their partner, friends,
family, and community.
And when they were in their 80s
the researchers asked them,
what are you most proud of
and what is your biggest regret?
- Many people said that they were proudest
of something to do with
their relationships.
So it could be, "I was a good
boss, I was a good parent,
I was a good friend, I was a good mentor."
Nobody said, "I made a fortune," right?
Nobody even said, you know,
"I won the Nobel Prize,"
which a few people did.
It wasn't about those badges
of achievement, right,
that we think of as, "Oh,
that's what we gotta get
to feel like we've had a meaningful life."
Everybody looking back
mentioned their relationships.
The biggest regret was
particularly among the men,
'cause this was the
World War II generation.
They said, "I wish I hadn't
spent so much time at work,
I wish I had spent more time
with the people I care about."
- So what about our original question?
Do achievements and money
really make us happy?
Well, according to the Harvard study,
badges of achievement do not
necessarily make us happier,
but doing meaningful work can.
And what about money?
Does that make us happier?
Well, there's a famous study from 2010
by Daniel Kahneman and Angus Deaton
that found that above an income
of around $75,000 a year,
there is no improvement whatever
in the measures of emotional wellbeing.
But 11 years later,
Matthew Killingsworth studied data
on 33,000 employed U.S. adults
and he found that higher incomes
corresponded to higher
levels of wellbeing.
So he wrote, "There was no evidence
for an experienced wellbeing
plateau above $75,000 a year,
contrary to some
influential past research."
In 2022, Kahneman and
Killingsworth set out
to resolve the conflict with
Barbara Mellers as a mediator.
When they analyzed Killingsworth's data,
they discovered an interesting pattern,
depending on how happy people
were relative to others,
earning more resulted in
different increases in happiness.
For each income level,
they divided people into groups
based on their happiness,
low, medium, high, and so on.
And they found that below a threshold
of roughly a hundred
thousand dollars a year,
a higher income was associated
with more happiness for all groups.
But if you go above that threshold,
then for the unhappiest group,
a further increase is not
associated with more happiness.
However, for all the happier groups,
higher incomes do seem to
lead to more happiness.
And the real twist is
that those who are the
happiest to start with
stand to gain the most
with increasing income.
Relationships, meaningful work,
and money all play a
role in our happiness.
So why can it be so hard
to realize just how
important relationships are?
- You know, if you think about it,
relationships have been there
since before we have memory, right?
So they're like the air we breathe,
we take 'em for granted.
So you don't think about that
as something you cultivate
in order to make yourself happy.
We don't think about that at all.
And yet, when we study it scientifically,
we find that that turns out
to be an enormous predictor
of happiness as well as physical health.
- What's gonna make you happy?
- Um.
- Uh.
- Being wealthy is definitely
a big aspect of it.
But that loving family is kind
of like the foundation of it.
You know what I mean?
- Realistically, money.
But like building deep connections
with people are what's going
to make me happy.
- [Derek] That's awesome.
- Having like good
relationships with other people.
- You raise a family.
- Have a family and provide.
- Friends and family.
- Seeing my family happy,
that's all I really care about.
- Giving back to the community
where you came from, the world.
- A strong family base just
to come home to every night.
- Yeah. I wanna get
married, have a ton of kids.
I want to-
- How many is a ton?
- Probably like five-ish, six.
- That's a-
- As many as I can afford.
(Derek laughs)
So.
- In fact, when I interviewed people,
I was pleasantly surprised
to see how many identified the
importance of relationships.
So if you could give people advice
on what to start doing today
to start being happier,
what suggestions would you make?
- To think about it as
analogous with physical fitness,
if you go out today, you don't come home
and say, "I'm done.
I don't ever have to
do that again," right?
It's like a practice, right?
That the people who were
best at relationships
were the people who made it a practice
day after day, week after week,
to stay connected to the
people they cared about.
You know, to talk on the
phone, to go for walks,
to have coffee, to do
whatever, to play basketball.
The people who took those
actions again and again regularly
were the people who stayed very connected
and stayed happy that way.
So what we propose is
that this is a practice we can cultivate
and that there are tiny
actions that people can take.
We have many stories of people
who thought that they were
no good at relationships,
that they were never
gonna have happy lives.
And then it changed.
And many times it changed
when they didn't expect it.
So like, we have a story about one man
who really didn't have a good marriage
and was kind of distant from his kids,
didn't have any friends.
And then when he retired,
he joined a gym and he
found this group of friends
that became, for the first
time, a kind of tribe for him.
And that's just one example
of how our lives take
these twists and turns
that we usually can't predict,
that we don't expect.
And many of those turns
are in positive directions.
The message that the science tells us
is don't give up on this
aspect of your life.
'cause many things can change at any age.
(transition beeps and chimes)